This phone is training a Transformer locally.
No cloud service.
No mobile-only inference runtime.
The same OA operation library, autograd engine, AdamW optimizer,
checkpoint format, and Vulkan kernels also run on an Intel desktop.
The same capability-driven runtime has NVIDIA, AMD, Intel, and
Qualcomm paths across discrete, integrated, and mobile GPUs.
The phone is not the product.
It is proof that the architecture travels.
GPU software is usually assembled from separate stacks for numerical
compute, machine learning, vision, audio, codecs, and presentation.
Each boundary introduces another data model, allocator, copy,
synchronization rule, and hardware backend.
Python makes the surface approachable, but crossing layers can still
fragment the work underneath.
The result is familiar: powerful accelerators, surrounded by glue.
OA tests a different idea: one GPU-first C++ and Python
framework over Vulkan.
Matrices, images, audio buffers, and video frames keep their
meaning, while one engine owns device memory, kernel selection,
graph execution, scheduling, and profiling.
Operations stay stateless.
Sessions own state.
Semantic work lowers into dispatches, transfers, barriers, resource
aliases, and explicit completion.
Capabilities are selected at runtime, and unsupported paths fail
visibly.
For Build Week, we made that claim physical.
OA Mobile Lab trains five small neural network architectures on an
Adreno phone: an RNN, a GRU, a Transformer,
a sparse mixture-of-experts Transformer, and Mamba-3.
A route passes only after forward, loss, backward, AdamW,
evaluation, autoregressive generation, checkpoint save, fresh-model
reload, and exact generation parity.
The controlled Transformer and mixture-of-experts contracts also
pass on Intel Iris Xe.
That result is difficult because training is not one kernel.
It is thousands of coupled decisions about shapes, lifetimes,
precision, descriptors, memory visibility, and device capabilities.
OA records the semantic operation first, then lowers it to an
executable Vulkan graph.
Recorded work and compiled replay amortize host work without
exposing a vendor policy through the high-level API.
The same substrate reaches far beyond the phone.
Audio paths decode, normalize, transform, and extract model-ready
features.
Vision operations preserve image semantics through transforms and
display.
Reinforcement learning connects native environments, models, and
metrics.
The early OaAlm pipeline turns text into skeletal motion
and exports USD.
Media, plotting, and viewer paths remain in the same system, with
shared values instead of a chain of opaque copies.
At the surface, the intent is deliberately simple.
Load an audio file.
Normalize it.
Compute a mel spectrogram.
Run a model.
The C++ and Python interfaces describe the same work, while
ownership, device choice, and synchronization remain explicit where
they matter.
We built this week with GPT-5.6 in
Codex as an engineering collaborator, not a code vending machine.
Codex audited ownership and synchronization, implemented vertical
changes, constructed differential tests, and repeatedly ran the real
hardware gates.
When the phone exposed corrupt Transformer learning that the desktop
tolerated, the investigation traced it to a thread-varying bindless
descriptor choice in a packed QKV shader.
We corrected the contract, rebuilt the signed app, and reran both
Qualcomm and Intel paths.
The loop was evidence, diagnosis, implementation, and proof.
OA 0.7.5 is a development preview, published
by Realm with a signed Android app, Python wheel, Linux packages,
and source.
It targets NVIDIA, AMD, Intel, and Qualcomm through Vulkan, with
verified scope declared per device.
Linux and Android ship now; Windows and macOS compute are planned.
One framework will not make every accelerator identical.
It can make more of them useful.
The accelerator you already own should be able to train.
This was a walkthrough, not the finish line.
The developer pages publish the working base, benchmarks, gaps, and
bounded roadmap: fifty Vision operations, thirteen Audio operation
candidates, five complete mobile training routes, CartPole PPO,
and early text-to-USD.
Explore the architecture, APIs, evidence, and roadmap at dev dot
realm dot software.